<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Orders, set dovvne by the Duke of Medina, Lord general of the Kings fleet, to be obserued in the voyage toward England. Translated out of Spanish into English by T.P.</title>
            <title>Instrucción general al armada. English</title>
            <author>Medina Sidonia, Alonso Pérez de Guzmán, duque de, 1550-1619.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114377</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849603</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849603</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14760</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09315)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 331:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Orders, set dovvne by the Duke of Medina, Lord general of the Kings fleet, to be obserued in the voyage toward England. Translated out of Spanish into English by T.P.</title>
                  <title>Instrucción general al armada. English</title>
                  <author>Medina Sidonia, Alonso Pérez de Guzmán, duque de, 1550-1619.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Orwin for Thomas Gilbert, dwelling in Fleetstreete neere to the signe of the Castle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Instrucción general al armada.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Orders appoynted for the Spanish fleet.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Armada, 1588 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14760:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:14760:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->
            <p>ORDERS, Set dovvne by the Duke of Medina, Lord general <hi>of the Kings Fleet, to be obſerued in</hi> the voyage toward England.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Spaniſh into Engliſh by <hi>T. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a galleon</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Thomas Orwin for Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Gilbert, dwelling in Fleetſtreete neere to the ſigne of the Caſtle. 1588.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14760:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 115 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:14760:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 115 -->
            <head>Don Alonſo Peres de guzman, the good Duke of Medina, Sidonia, Countie of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bla, Marques of Caſheſhe in Africa, Lord of the Citie Sainct Lucar, Captaine generall of the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Sea, of the Coſt of Andaluzia, and of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of his Maieſtie, and Knight of the honorable order of the golden Fleece.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Do ordaine and commaund, that the generall Maiſters of the field, all Captaines, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Campe and of the Sea, Pilats, Maiſters, Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, Marriners, and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, &amp; whatſoeuer other people for the land or Sea ſeruice commeth in this Armie, al the time that it indureth, ſhall be thus gouerned, as hereafter followeth, viz.</p>
            <p>Firſt, and before all things,<note place="margin">The cauſe of the Iorney.</note> it is to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by al the aboue named from the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the loweſt: that the principall founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and cauſe that hath moued the King his Maieſtie to make and continue this iorney, hath been and is, to ſerue God, and to returne vnto his Church a great many of contrite
<pb facs="tcp:14760:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 116 -->
ſoules that are oppreſſed by the Heretikes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to our holy Catholike faith, which haue them ſubiects to their ſects, and vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe: and for that euery one, may put his eyes vpon this marke, as we are bound, I do command and much deſire euery one, to giue charge vnto the inferiours and thoſe vnder their charge to imbarke themſelues,<note place="margin">Their Shrift.</note> being ſhriuen, and hauing receiued the <hi>Sacrament</hi> with competent contrition for their ſinnes: by the which contrition and zeale to do GOD ſuch great ſeruice, he will carie and guide vs to his great glorie: which is, that which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly and principally is pretended.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">For auoyding blaſphemie and raging oathes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note>In like maner, I do charge and command you, to haue particular care, that no Soldier, Marriner, or other, that ſerueth in this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, do blaſpheme, or rage againſt God, or our Lady, or any of the Saincts, vpon paine that he ſhall therefore ſharply be corrected, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well chaſtened, as it ſhall ſeeme beſt vnto vs: and for other oathes of leſſe qualitie, the gouernours in the ſame ſhips they go in, ſhall procure to remedie all: they ſhall puniſh them in taking away their allowance of wine, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, as they ſhall thinke good. And for that the moſt occaſions come by play, you ſhal publikly prohibit it, eſpecially the games that are forbidden:<note place="margin">Debarring play.</note> and that none do play in the night, by no meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14760:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 116 -->And to auoyd inconueniences that might enſue in this Armie and force of his Maieſtie, if that the here written were not put for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, by theſe preſents I do command, that particularly and generally, all quarrels, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, defiances and iniuries that are &amp; haue been before this day, and vntill the publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof, of all perſons as well by Sea as land,<note place="margin">Suppreſſing of quarels.</note> of greater or leſſe qualities be ſuppreſſed and ſuſpended, ſo that none goeth in this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie for the time that this voyage continueth and laſteth, although they be olde quarels: yet for my expreſſe commaundement ſhall breake this truce and forbearance of Armes, direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or indirectly, vpon payne of diſobedience and incurring into high treaſon, and dye therefore.</p>
            <p>In like maner I do giue charge,<note place="margin">Digraces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded.</note> that abord the ſhippes there bee not any thing offered to the diſgrace of any man.</p>
            <p>Declaring herewithall, that there cannot bee any diſgrace imputed to any man for any thing that ſhalbe offered, nor yet be a reproach whatſoeuer happeneth abord any ſhip.</p>
            <p>And for that it is knowne that great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces and offence groweth vnto God,<note place="margin">Carying of common wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> by conſenting that common women and ſuch like go in like Armies:</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14760:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 117 -->I do ordaine and commaund, that there be none imbarked nor caried in the Armie: And if that any will carrie them, I do commaund the Captaines and Maiſters of the ſhippes, not to conſent thereto: who ſo doth, or diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth therewith, ſhalbe grieuouſly puniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Giuing the good morow.</note>The companie of euery ſhip, one euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the breake of the day, according to the cuſtome, ſhall giue the good morrowe by the maine maſt, and at night the <hi>Aue Maria:</hi> and ſome dayes the <hi>Salue Regine:</hi> or at leaſt, the Saterdaies with a Lettenie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Auoyding all occaſions of Scandale.</note>And foraſmuch as it importeth for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation and good ſucceſſe of this armie, that there be betweene the Soldiers and Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners much confirmed friendſhip, and ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie that there bee not any difference, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſions of murmuring, I commaund it to bee publiſhed that no bodie do carrie any Dagger, nor thwart one another, or giue any occaſions, but that all do obey the ſuperiour Officers: and if any <hi>Scandale</hi> or offence come, he that was the beginner, ſhall ſtraightly bee puniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Order for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture.</note>When the <hi>Gallion Sainct Marten,</hi> wherein my ſelfe go, Admirall of this Fleet, doth make a ſigne with a peece of Ordinance, it ſhall bee a ſigne of departure for the whole Fleete, that
<pb facs="tcp:14760:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 117 -->
ſounding their Trumpets ſhall follow with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loſing time, and without comming fowell of each other, and cutting ſayle ſhall doe the like: hauing great care of the Sands and Catchops, carrying their Boates &amp; Skiffes readie for any thing that may happen.</p>
            <p>Being from the land a ſea borde,<note place="margin">Order for comming to the Admirall.</note> euery ſhip ſhall come to leyward, ſaluting the Admirall to know what he wil commaund: &amp; demaund the word, without going a head the Admiral, either in the day or in the night, but to haue great care to his ſayling.</p>
            <p>Euery afternoone they ſhal repayre to their Admirals to take the word,<note place="margin">Taking the word.</note> and to knowe if there be any thing to do.</p>
            <p>And for that ſo many great Shippes, and ſo great may be, cannot come euery day with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bording one another: to auoyde the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that may followe, the Generall of each <hi>Squadron</hi> ſhall haue particular care, to take the word in time, to giue it vnto the Shippes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their charge.</p>
            <p>The Admiral ſhalbe ſaluted with Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, of them that haue them: if not,<note place="margin">Hayling the Admirall.</note> with their Whiſtles: and the people to hallowe one after another, and aunſwering them ſhall ſalute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and if it be towards night to demaund
<pb facs="tcp:14760:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 118 -->
the word, and taking it ſhall ſalute one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in time, and depart to giue roume to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that follow.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The watch word.</note>If it happeneth ſome daies that winde wil not ſuffer to take the word of the Admirall or Admirals, they ſhall haue for euery day in the weeke the words following.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Sunday. <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Monday. <hi>The holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tueſday. <hi>The holy Trinitie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wenſday. <hi>Sainct Iames.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thurſday. <hi>The Angels.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Friday. <hi>All Saincts.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Saterday. <hi>Our Ladie.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diſpoſing of their Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons.</note>And for that it importeth that all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies doe go cloſe together, I doe commaund that the General and wings with great care, do procure to carie the <hi>Squadrons</hi> as nigh and in as good order, as is poſſible: and the Ship and Pinneſſes of the charge of <hi>Don Antonio de Hartado de Mendoſa,</hi> keepe next vnto the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall, except ſixe: whereof, two ſhall followe the Admirall <hi>Don Pedro de Valdezi,</hi> and two the Admirall of <hi>Martine Bretendona:</hi> the other two the Admirall of <hi>Ioan Gomes de Medina:</hi> the which ſhall be appoynted preſently, and haue great care to repart themſelues, without the one thwarting the other: and the <hi>Squadron</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:14760:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 118 -->
the Hulkes ſhall go alwaies in the mids.</p>
            <p>That no ſhippe of the Nauie,<note place="margin">Departure without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe.</note> nor any that goeth with them ſhall depart, without my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe: And I do commaunde vpon payne of death, and loſſe of goodes, that if by chaunce with a ſtorme any bee driuen to depart before they come to the <hi>Cape Finiſter,</hi> that then they followe their courſe to the ſayd <hi>Cape,</hi> where they ſhall haue my order what to doe: or elſe they ſhall ſayle to the <hi>Groyne,</hi> where they ſhall haue it.</p>
            <p>In departing from the <hi>Groyne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Rande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous.</note> they ſhall ſet their courſe for <hi>Silley,</hi> and procure to make the Sowtherſide of it, hauing great care of their ſounding: And if by chaunce in this courſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhippe or ſhippes doe looſe the Fleete, they ſhall not returne into <hi>Spayne,</hi> in any manner, vpon payne of death and the loſſe of goodes, and taken for Traytors, but followe the courſe, and make to the Southward of the ſayd Iland. And if any ſuch doe thinke the Nauie to bee aſterne of him, he ſhall detaine himſelfe in the ſame height playing vp and downe, and not to depart from his courſe.</p>
            <p>And if it bee thought that the Nauie is a head, then ſhall you ſeeke them in <hi>Monts bay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Directions from Monts bay.</note> which is betwixt the Lands end and the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard,</hi> there ſhall you haue the whole Nauie, or
<pb facs="tcp:14760:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 119 -->
intelligence what he ſhall do: and yet for all this, if he do not meete with the Nauie, yet ſhall he finde Pinneſſes with order what ſhal be done.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Watching of the Admirall.</note>In the night there ſhall be great vigilance for the Admiral, to ſee if ſhe change her courſe, or make about. Before ſhe goeth about, ſhe will ſhoot off a peece: and being about, wil put foorth an other light vpon the Poope a parte from the Lanterne: who that doth ſee it, ſhall aunſwer with an other light.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Markes by lights.</note>When he doth take away Bonnets, or ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the Sayles, he ſhall ſhewe lights, one in the Poope, and other two ſhrowed high.</p>
            <p>When that for any occaſion he ſhall ſtrike all Sayles, he ſhall ſhewe three lights, one in the toppe, an other in the Shrowdes, and the third in the Fore-caſtle: and the reſt ſhall ſhew it, with putting foorth a light each vpon his Poope.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Shooting off peeces.</note>If any Ship haue any occaſion to ſtrike al her Sayles in the night, he ſhall ſhoote off a great peece, and put out a Lanterne all night, and thoſe that are nigheſt vnto him ſhal ſhew lights, for that other may procure it, and ſhall take in the Sayles till day: And if neceſſitie be great, ſhal ſhoot off an other peece, and thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:14760:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 119 -->
that do ſee it, ſhall aunſwer with other two lights, making the like boord.</p>
            <p>When the Admirall will haue any commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, he wil make a ſigne,<note place="margin">Signes by Flagges.</note> putting a flagge in the after miſne neere the Lanterne, and ſo they ſhall repayre vnto him to know what he would haue. If (which God for his mercie permit not) there happen any Shippe to take fire, the next vnto her ſhall make from her,<note place="margin">Remedie for fire.</note> ſending firſt their Boates and Skiffes to ſuccour and helpe, and ſo ſhall all the reſt.</p>
            <p>They ſhall haue particular care to put foorth their fire in euery Shippe,<note place="margin">To put forth fire.</note> before the Sunne go downe.</p>
            <p>In taking of their allowance of victualls,<note place="margin">Allowance of victualls.</note> the Souldiers ſhall let them that haue the charge thereof, to deliuer it, ſo that the ſayd Souldiers ſhall not go downe to take it, nor chooſe it perforce, as in times they haue done: and for this cauſe ſhall bee preſent the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant or Corporall of the companie or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies where they are, for auoyding diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and that timely they haue their portions: ſo that before night euery bodie may haue ſupped.</p>
            <p>That no ſhippe nor other veſſel of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, nor of any of thoſe,<note place="margin">Anckoring or harborough, or going a ſhore.</note> that goeth ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:14760:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 120 -->
my iuriſdiction, ſhall not bee ſo bold to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into any Harborough, ancker, nor goe a ſhore, without the Admirall doth do it firſt, or with my ſpeciall leaue, vpon payne of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Armour kept cleane.</note>The Corenalls of the fielde, Captaines, Lieftenants, Enſigne and officers, muſt haue particular care, that the Souldiers haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies their Armour cleane, readie and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for time of neceſſitie: cauſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make them cleane twiſe euery weeke, and vſing themſelues with them in ſuch ſort, that they may be expert at the time of neede.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">For preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fire.</note>And for that in the way order ſhal be giuen in what forme euery man ſhall put himſelfe, if we do fight, I do commaund that particular care bee had, aduiſing the Gunners to haue halfe Buts with water and vineger, as is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed, with Bonnets and olde Sayles, and wet Mantels to defend fire, that as often is throwne, as to haue the like care to haue ſhot made in good quantitie,<note place="margin">Shot, pouder and Match.</note> and that pouder and match be readie for Ship, and Soldiers of the ſtore by waight, meaſure and length: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order that euery Ship hath to deliuer vnto him that hath the charge thereof according to vſe and cuſtome.</p>
            <p>Alſo I order and commaund that there bee
<pb facs="tcp:14760:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 120 -->
a care,<note place="margin">Roume cleane of Cheſtes and Cardes.</note> that all Souldiers haue their roume cleane and vnpeſtered of Cheſtes, and other thinges, without conſenting in any caſe to haue Cardes: and if there be any, to be taken away preſently: neither permit them to the Marriners: and if the Souldiers haue any, let me bee aduertiſed, that I may commaund them to be taken away.</p>
            <p>And for that the Marriners muſt reſorte vnto their worke, tackle and Nauigation,<note place="margin">Marriners lodgings.</note> it is conuenient that their lodgings bee in the vpper workes of the poope, and fore-caſtle, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the Souldiers will trouble them in the voyage.</p>
            <p>The Artillarie muſt ſtand in very good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and reparted amongſt the Gunners,<note place="margin">Lockers for the Gunners.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing al charged with their balles, and nigh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery peece his locker, wherein to put his Shot and neceſſaries, and to haue great care to the Cartrages of euery Peece, for not chaunging or not taking fire: and that the Ladles and Spunges be readie at hand.</p>
            <p>Euery Ship ſhall carrie two Boates la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſtones,<note place="margin">Stones and halfe pipes.</note> to throw to profite in the time of fight on the Decke, Fore-caſtle or toppes, according to his burden: and ſhall carrie two halfe Pipes, to fil them with water in the day of Battell, and repart them amongſt the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,
<pb facs="tcp:14760:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 121 -->
or other places, as ſhall be thought neceſſarie, and nigh vnto them olde clothes or couerings, which with wetting may deſtroy any kinde of fire.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Wild fire.</note>That the wilde fire be reparted to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple moſt expert, that we haue for the vſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at due time: for that if it be not ouer-ſeene, giuing charge thereof to thoſe that doth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, and ſuch as we know can tel how to vſe it: otherwiſe it may happen to great daunger.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Nauie cloſe together.</note>By the commaundement that no ſhip ſhall go a head the Admirall, at the leaſt in the night, none ſhall tarrie a ſterne the Vice-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall, and euery one to haue a care to the trimming of his Sayles, according to the charge he hath, and the ſayling of his ſhip: for the much that it importeth that all our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie do go cloſe as poſſible as they may: and in this the Captaines, Maiſters, and Pilates muſt haue ſuch great care, as of them is hope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reading theſe inſtructions.</note>Theſe my inſtructions are deliuered vnto euery Shippe, and haue their copie firmed by my hand, and regeſtred by my Secretarie, the which ſhall be read by euery Purſer of euery Shippe publikely, to come to the note of all Souldiers and Marriners, whereby they may not pretend ignorance: and to the ſayd
<pb facs="tcp:14760:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 121 -->
Purſers I ordaine and command, that thrice in the weeke they be bound to reade theſe my inſtructions publikly, and that they take wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the fulfilling hereof, vpon paine of him that doth the contrarie, ſhall receiue puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the example of others.</p>
            <p>All the aboue ſaid, we commaund to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, and bee kept without any breach for the ſeruice of his Maieſtie, none to breake them or any parte thereof in no manner, vpon payne they ſhalbe ſeuerely puniſhed, euery one according to his eſtate and offence: all others reſerued to our diſcretion.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Made in the <hi>Gallion Sainct Marten,</hi> at the Road of <hi>Belline,</hi> 
                  <date>the 28. of May. 1588.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Th. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
